DANIELA OPITZ

Instituto Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo (+56) 965 025 054 \(\sharphi\) dan.opitz@gmail.com http://daniopitz.cl

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is situated at the intersection of human mobility and data science, with a specific emphasis on leveraging machine learning techniques to address challenges in transportation planning. I utilize advanced computational approaches to analyze mobility patterns and enhance transportation systems. Additionally, I have a strong interest in the field of computer vision and in applying data science for social well-being. In the academic realm, I have taught courses in Introduction to Programming in Python, Introduction to Computer Vision, and Information Visualization. My prior experience includes reasearch in astronomy, specifically in image processing and the study of star motion.

EDUCATION

2018	Ph.D. in Physics , University of New South Wales, Australia Thesis: Imaging and Astrometry for the Coolest Brown Dwarfs Advisor: Dr. Christopher Tinney
2011	B.Sc. in Astronomy, University of Chile

PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

2020 - Present	Assistant Professor Instituto Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo
2018 - 2019	R&D Researcher Instituto Data Science, Telefónica R&D - Universidad del Desarrollo
2017	Data Analyst Direction of Information Technologies and Communication, University of Chile

FUNDING AND AWARDS

Research Grants

2022 - 2023	Fondo de Innovación para la Competitividad Regional (FIC-R), 40043796-0 Digital management of mobility for the city Principal Investigator
2022 - 2024	ANID-Fondecyt de Iniciación, 11220799 Leaving no one behind: measuring digital inequalities using mobile phone records Principal Investigator
2020 - 2022	ANID-Subvención a Instalación en la Academia, PAI77190057 Strengthening of research and teaching in data science in the area of smart cities, top-ranked Principal Investigator
2020	Severo Ochoa Mobility grant To visit the Barcelona Supercomputing Center
2013 - 2017	Ph.D top-up scholarship, UNSW Exoplanetary Science Group
2012 - 2017	ANID-Becas Chile fellowship

Telescope Proposals

2016	Opitz, D., Tinney, C. G., Faherty, J. & Gelino, C. GS-2016B-C-2 Astrometry and Binarity of WISE Y dwarfs with MCAO Gemini South, GEMS-GSAOI
2015	Opitz, D., Tinney, C. G., Faherty, J. & Gelino, C. GS-2015B-Q-47 Astrometry and Binarity of WISE Y dwarfs with MCAO Gemini South, GEMS-GSAOI
Awards	
2014	Best student poster, Second Chilean Graduate Student Conference, Australia
2014	Best student poster, The Astronomical Society of Australia Annual Meeting
2009 - 2010	Claudio Vicuña award, University of Chile
2007 - 2009	Moisés Mellado award, University of Chile
2004 - 2010	Bicentenario scholarhip, Government of Chile

PUBLICATIONS

Refereed Publications

Refereed Fublications		
2023	Graells-Garrido, E., Opitz , D. , Rowe, F & Arriagada, J. A data fusion approach with mobile phone data for updating travel survey-based mode split estimates <i>Transport Research Part C: Emerging Technologies</i> https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trc.2023.104285	
2022	Graells-Garrido, E., Shifanella R. Opitz , D. & Rowe, F. Measuring the local complementarity of population, amenities and digital activities to identify and understand urban areas of interest. <i>Environment and Planning B: Urban Analytics and City Science</i> , 50(4), 942-957 https://doi.org/10.1177/23998083221117830	
2020	Opitz, D. , Graells-Garrido, E., & Pérez-Messina, I. Toward Characterizing Cities with Social Media Images Using Activity Recognition, Topic Modeling and Visualization. <i>In Companion Proceedings of the Web Conference 2020 (pp. 688-693)</i> . https://doi.org/10.1145/3451964.3451972	
2016	Opitz, D. , Tinney, C., Faherty, J., Sweet, S., Gelino, C. & Kirkpatrick J. D. Searching for Binary Y Dwarfs with the Gemini Multi-conjugate Adaptive Optics System (GeMS). <i>The Astrophysical Journal</i> , 819(1), 17. https://doi.org/10.3847/0004-637X/819/1/17	
2011	Opitz, D. & Gallardo, J. Lithium Depletion Boundary Under Rotation And Spots Coverage. Boletin de la Asociacion Argentina de Astronomia La Plata Argentina, 54,	

Manuscripts Under Review

93-96.

2024 Cotton, D., Bailey J., Kedziora-Chudczer, L., Bott, K., De Horta, A., Filcek, N., Marshall, J., Melville, G., Buzasi, D., Boiko, I., Borsato, N., Perkins, J., **Opitz**, **D**., et al. Polarization Position Angle Standard stars: a Reassessment of θ and its Variability for Seventeen Stars Based on a Decade of Observations

Manuscripts in Preparation for Submission

2024	Opitz, D., Graells-Garrido, E., Arriagada, J., Rivas, M. & Meza, N. e-Scooter Effects
	on Public Transport Demand: A Case Study in Santiago, Chile
2024	Opitz, D., Marín, C., Campos, D., Graells-Garrido, E., Bravo, L. et al. Urban
	Transformations: Evaluating the impact of Santiago's principal bike lanes on city
	dynamics.

Conference Proceedings

2022	Urrejola, S., Del Campo-Smith, M., Duran, E., Asahi, T., Opitz, D. & Lobos, L. Scratch Assay Image Analysis Automation. 26th UK Conference on Medical Image Understanding and Analysis.
2015	Opitz, D. & Tinney, C. Searching for Binary Y dwarfs with the Gemini Multi-Conjugate Adaptive Optics System. <i>IAU General Assembly, 22, 2241608.</i>
2014	Opitz, D. & Tinney, C. Searching for Binary Y dwarfs with the Gemini Multi-Conjugate Adaptive Optics System. Cambridge Workshop on Cool Stars, Stellar Systems, and the Sun, 18, 1027.

Other Publications

2023 Graells-Garrido, E. & **Opitz**, **D**. La ciudad a vuelo de pájaro: ciencia de datos para planificación urbana. *Bits de Ciencia*, 24, 9-14
https://www.dcc.uchile.cl/difusion/revista/24

TALKS

2024	Bikeway Planning: The Role of Mobile Phone Data. Urban Beers, Santiago, Chile.
2023	Gestión Digital de la Movilidad para la Ciudad. Metropolitan Regional Council (GORE), Santiago, Chile.
2023	Gestión Digital de la Movilidad para la Ciudad. Closing event for the FIC-R project, Santiago, Chile.
2023	PLUMAS: Urban platform of mobility, analysis and simulation. Barcelona Supercomputing Center 2023, Barcelona, Spain.
2020	Toward characterizing cities with social media images. The Web Conference 2020, Taipei, Taiwan.
2018	From astronomy to data science. Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile.
2017	Measuring distances to the coolest stars with adaptive optics. Chile Wic, Woman In Computing, Santiago, Chile.
2017	Imaging and astrometry for the coolest stars (Invited). II Chilean Gemini Users Meeting & Workshop, La Serena, Chile.
2015	Searching for binary Y dwarfs with GeMS. The 2015 Australian Gemini, Magellan, and Keck Science Symposium, Sydney, Australia.
2011	Lithium depletion boundary under rotation and spots coverage. I Annual Meeting Between The Chilean Astronomical Society and The Argentinian Astronomical Association, San Juan, Argentina.

TECHNOLOGY TRANSFER

2023	Digital management of mobility for the city: a visualization tool for urban mobility
	based on mobile phone records. Metropolitan Regional Government (GORE)
2023	Aves: a Python library for Analysis, Visualization, Education, and Support
2022	SpotPaySolutions: estimation of potential new payment points using transaction data
	and machine learning algorithms. Transbank.
2020 - 2022	Metamobility: characterization of users using mobile phone records and machine
	learning models. Telefónica Tech.
2019	AI Readiness, diagnosis of adoption of AI in companies. AmCham Chile.
2018	Smart-agro: characterization of agriculture crops using multi-spectral images and
	computer vision algorithms. Telefónica Tech.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2023 - 2024	Visualization of Information	Universidad del Desarrollo
2019 - 2023	Introduction to Programming	Universidad del Desarrollo
2018 - 2020	Introduction to Computer Vision	Universidad del Desarrollo
2019	Introduction to Python	Telefónica Tech

SUPERVISION

Research Assistance

2023	Natalia Meza, Tools for processing and analyzing BIP transaction data, University of
	Chile
2023	Matilde Rivas, Aves: analysis, and visualization.
2023	Cesar Marín, Digital management of mobility for the city, Data Science Institute,
	Universidad del Desarrollo
2022 - 2023	Daniela Campos, Digital management of mobility for the city, Data Science Institute,
	Universidad del Desarrollo.

Master of Science

Expected 2024 Sebastián Olmos, Superfly: System for visualizing multivariate mobility flows in a city, Master of Science in Computer Science, University of Chile

Master of Professional Studies

2024	Claudio Gaete, Geographical lifetime value for Transbank, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2024	Camila Soto, Geographical lifetime value for Transbank, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2023	Felipe Guzmán, Estimation of public transport demand using machine learning methods, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2023	Effry Vigorena, Estimation of public transport demand using machine learning methods, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2023	Fabian Nova, Assessing travel time changes with the introduction of a new metro station, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2023	Wilder Prado, Assessing travel time changes with the introduction of a new metro station, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2023	Fernando Nachbauer, <i>Impact of crimes on economic activity</i> , Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2023	Javier Zacarias, <i>Impact of crimes on economic activity</i> , Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2023	Jorge Adrián Fernandez, Detection of globular cluster sequences in Virgo, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo
2022	Sebastián Urrejola, Scratch assay image analysis automation, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2022	Marcelo Medel, Personalized product recommendation system in an e-commerce, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2022	Alejandro Mendez, Classification and prediction of tree types in the Roosevelt Reserve using cartographic data, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2022	Eduardo Inostroza, Prediction of cardiovascular diseases in adults using machine learning methods, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2021	Roxana Godoy, Development of a customer retention model for a Telecommunications company, Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.
2021	Sergio Arancibia, Impact of land use on mobility in the Metropolitan Region during pandemic times. Master in Data Science, Universidad del Desarrollo.

${\bf Undergraduate}$

Expected 2024	Elías Moreno, Simulating the Santiago of the Future: Implementation of a mobility
	simulator using mobile phone digital traces, Computer Science Engineering, University
	of Chile
2021	José Tomás Vasquez, Data Science in Transportation Logistics for Link Projects, In-
	dustrial Engineering, Universidad del Desarrollo

SERVICE & OUTREACH

2020	Reviewer internal research projects, University of Bío-Bío, Chile
2014 - 2016	Vice president & secretary of The Chilean Student Association at UNSW, Sydney,
	Australia
2009 - 2012	Science communicator for Explora-Conicyt exhibitions, Chile
2010	Science communicator for Observatorio Astronómico Nacional, Chile

REFERENCES

Professor Christopher Tinney Head of Exoplanetary Science, UNSW Research Group University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia c.tinney@unsw.edu.au

Professor Francisco Rowe Lead of the Geographic Data Science Lab, Department of Geography and Planning University of Liverpool, UK fcorowe@liverpool.ac.uk

Associate Professor Loreto Bravo Director of Data Science Institute, Faculty of Engineering Universidad del Desarrollo, Chile bravo@udd.cl